<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached upon the thirtieth of January, 1694/5, in the parish of S. in the county of Norfolk by Samuel Snowden ...</title>
            <author>Iraeneus, junior.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60704</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4397</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38262</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17245132</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17245132</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106293</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60704)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106293)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1101:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached upon the thirtieth of January, 1694/5, in the parish of S. in the county of Norfolk by Samuel Snowden ...</title>
                  <author>Iraeneus, junior.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Heptinstall for Edward Giles, bookseller in Norwich ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Iraeneus, junior, is a pseudonym of Samuel Snowden.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXLVI, 3-4 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106293:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106293:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached upon the Thirtieth of <hi>January,</hi> 1694/5. IN The Pariſh of <hi>S.</hi> in the County OF NORFOLK.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Samuel Snowden</hi> Rector <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Heptinſtall</hi> for <hi>Edward Giles,</hi> Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller in <hi>Norwich,</hi> near the <hi>Market-Place.</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:106293:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106293:2"/>
            <head>To the Inhabitants of <hi>N.</hi> and <hi>S.</hi> in the County of <hi>Norfolk.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MY Hearts deſire and prayer to God for you is, that you may be ſaved; to promote which end, the moſt powerful Doctrine abſtracted from a good Life, too often proves but a weak expedient, the contexture of the mouth, being ſo eaſily unravelled by the work of the hands. For whatever we ſay, yet Men are apt to look on us, and do likewiſe, and to walk as they have us for an example: Which is more eſpecially true, when we tread awry, or make any falſe ſteps. I wiſh I could in all reſpects propound my ſelf a pattern fit for your imitation; That with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> I might ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſire you not only to be almoſt, but altogether ſuch as I am. But who can pretend to give ſuch advice, that is encompaſſed with ſo many conſtant defects and infirmities; yet I ſhould be glad to ſee you follow me, ſo far as I fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt, and that I might lead you to him who is the way to himſelf. The deſign of this diſcourſe (lately deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered among you) was to warn you not to build, or lay the foundation of your joy and hope upon the Sand, and if you will believe this word of God and keep it, <hi>viz.</hi> [put
<pb facs="tcp:106293:3"/>not your truſt in Princes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] you will be built upon a rock that can never be ſhaken; the wiſedom of which counſel hath been juſtified by too ſad and freſh an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I mean the fall of a great Perſon in our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who had not long ſince the Imperial Crown ſet upon her Head, and was anointed with Oyl of gladneſs, (to all who had any value for their Religion and Liberties) or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps it was to her Burial, but if not, yet we ſee it could not prevent it, when the Lord commanded her Breath to go forth, and her Body to return to its Earth. It may be we lean'd too hard, and relied too much upon our ſtaff, which made it buckle under us, and cauſed the Lord to be ſo far diſpleaſed with us, that he hath taken away the deſire of our Eyes, and delight of our Hearts with a ſtroke; our <hi>Jachin,</hi> one of the Pillars of our hope from us. May we not in this, or any other way provoke him ſo far to anger againſt us, but that he may continue our <hi>Boaz</hi> to us. But thus many times Parents love their Children to death, being over-kind to them, and fond of them, till they kill them with their kindneſs, and cruſh them with their embraces, provoking God to pluck them thence and leave them in a diſconſolate eſtate, who know not how to be comforted, becauſe they are not, whom methinks I hear thus complaining. My Children are taken away, and do you ask me what I ail. Upon this foundation we deſigned to build our Names and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, here we had Content and Happineſs laid up for
<pb facs="tcp:106293:3"/>many Years, but this Night their Breath is gone forth, and all our thoughts and deſigns are periſhed. Our Pitchers (which we perceive were but earthen Veſſels) are broken at the Fountain, ſo that all our purpoſes and projections are like water ſpilt upon the ground. Here's a Parable, and you need not go far for the Interpretation of it. We have had the Perſons of our Princes in ſo great admiration, becauſe of thoſe great advantages they have brought to theſe Nations, that we have forgot the Lord, who was the principal Author of our Deliverance, for which ſin perhaps his anger is ſo remarkably broken out againſt us, which hath this day cauſed our Cup to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow with the tears of our Complaints, and many bitter cries to be heard among us, the Subjects mourning for their Sovereign, becauſe She is not, ſtiling themſelves <hi>Icabods</hi> for the Glory is departed from our <hi>Iſrael.</hi> But whither are our thoughts wandred and our Pen fled? But no wonder, if the ſenſe of our loſs hath made ſuch impreſſions upon our Spirits as to tranſport us beyond our ſelves and ſubject. But upon a due recollection, let's mourn for thoſe ſins which have done us this incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble injury, if the effects and fruits of them be ſo bad, what's the root of bitterneſs from whence they are ſprung? Let us pluck it up, and if poſſible, not leave ſo much as a ſtump in the Earth. We have a Prince yet left upon the Throne to go in and out before us, and to fight our Battels, <hi>but if we ſhall ſtill do wickedly, we ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:106293:4"/>be deſtroyed both we and our King, 1</hi> Sam. <hi>12.25.</hi> And this would dip our miſeries with a ſcarlet die, and crimſon tincture, cauſing them to be double hatcht, and our latter ends worſe than our beginning.</p>
            <p>But perhaps 'twill be ſaid, we have too many State<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers which have troubled the World with ſuch Papers and Pamphlets, when the Kingdom of God and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs thereof, were a more proper ſubject for their Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and Theme for the Pulpit.</p>
            <p>How little I have troubled you with things of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from thence,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit. 3.1.</hi> Put them in mind of being ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities and Powers to obey Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> when it was not neceſſary to mind you of being ſubject to Principalities and Powers, I leave your ſelves to be judges. But if the duty I owe to God and You, be not ſufficient to vouch me, let the objection avail as far as it can againſt me. Yet of this I am ſure, that I am indiſpenſibly bound by virtue of the Office I bear among you, by all the ways I can to promote your future welfare, and everlaſting intereſts. But if I have better conſulted them in a more practical Diſcourſe ſcattered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, which is the voice of one crying to you, prepare ye the way of<note n="*" place="margin">Antidote againſt the Poiſon and Sting of Death.</note> death and make that path ſtreight; I would the more earneſtly recommend it to your diligent peruſal, which will be no ſmall encouragement to me to ſtudy, how I may be moſt of all ſerviceable to you in the Work of the Goſpel; which as it is the duty, ſo I hope ſhall be ever the deſign of</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Febr. 8. 1694/5.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your moſt Faithfull Friend and Servant <hi>Sam. Snowden.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106293:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Pſalm. 146. v. 3, 4.</bibl>
                  <p>Put not your truſt in Princes, nor in the Son of Man, in whom there is no help; his breath goeth forth, he returneth to his Earth, in that very day his thoughts periſh.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THAT the condition of Mankind is not an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and independing State, our daily occurring wants, and conſtant recourſes to Heaven for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies are ſufficient proofs. The plants of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs (whatever they may be when they ſhall become Trees of Life in the Paradiſe of God) are but yet tender. Yea, though they be rooted and grounded in the Faith, will not be able to bear the ſhock, or weather thoſe blaſts, which the Prince of the Power of the Air raiſes againſt them, if not ſtaked with ſupports of greater ſtrength, and better conſiſtency than themſelves. St. <hi>Peter</hi> was the rock of the Church, yet if the rock of Ages (I mean our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour) had not held him faſt, when like the trembling. Pillars of the Earth he was ſhaken, he muſt have fallen.<note place="margin">Joh. <hi>9.6.</hi>
               </note> Yea, he had been as chaff before the wind, when Satan had deſired to winnow him, had not he prayed that his Faith might not fail.</p>
            <p>The Wiſedom of this juſt Man, I mean, the Pſalmiſt, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in directing us to the ſureſt object of our truſt, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us to be wiſe Maſter-builders, not to lay the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our hope in the duſt: <hi>Put not your truſt in Princes, or in the Son of Man, &amp;c.</hi> But rather to erect our hope upon that which is elect and precious laid in <hi>Sion,</hi> in him whoſoever believeth he ſhall not be aſhamed: <hi>Yea rather happy is the Man who hath the God of Jacob for his help,</hi> v. 5. He would not have us go down to <hi>Egypt</hi> for relief, nor
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106293:5"/>reſt upon a broken ſtaff, or bruiſed reed, which will not only buckle under us and deceive us, when we lean too hard upon it; but will alſo run into our ſides and pierce us through with grief at the conſideration of our diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For if we lay too great a ſtreſs, a dead and maſſy weight upon a weak foundation, we ſhall ſoon find a ſet in our Building, the Fabrick will ſink for want of a ſufficient baſis, and bottom to ſuſtain it.</p>
            <p>The Pſalm is a Song of Praiſe,<note place="margin">The Title which the <hi>Septuag.</hi> gives this Pſalm is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Praiſe ye <hi>Jah.</hi>
               </note> compoſed as have been thought, to bleſs God for the reduction of his People out of Captivity, which was a proper time for <hi>Jacob</hi> to rejoice, and for <hi>Iſrael</hi> to be glad. Pſal. 14. v. 7. <hi>When the Lord bringeth back the captivity of his People,</hi> Jacob <hi>ſhall rejoice and</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſhall be glad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next to his reſolve of bleſſing God, he gives advice in what we may not, and in what we may truſt, and depend upon, which counſel he juſtifies in both reſpects, with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted arguments taken partly from the ſtate and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Man: Partly from the Power, Providence, Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Eternal Soveraignty of the Divine Being.</p>
            <p>The Text tells us where we muſt not caſt anchor, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 'tis no ſecure harbour to winter in, nor can we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that lee weather the point, ſeeing no ſmall ſtorms are like to lay upon, and endanger us in our Voyage. <hi>Put not your truſt in Princes, nor in the Son of Man,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> From whence we obſerve, that it's a vain thing to repoſe our confidence in Man, though in the higheſt exaltation, for relief.</p>
            <p>This is to ſeek for it where it is not to be found, and to ſuck at a breaſt for Conſolation, which hath none of that ſincere Milk. Suppoſe we get under the ſhadow of theſe wings, alas, they are too full of faint plumes, and ſick feathers, either to brood or defend us: Nor can we be ever ſafe under the ſhelter of ſuch withering and decaying plants. They may truly ſay as is ſaid in another caſe, 'tis not ours
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106293:5"/>to give. Or as the King to the Woman in the Siege of <hi>Samaria,</hi> if the Lord does not help thee, whence ſhould I? In my diſcourſe upon this Theme, I ſhall firſt ſhow you, that in our preſent ſtate and circumſtances we ſtand in need of help and relief. Some to truſt in, and to flee to for ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly. Conſidering Men in their higheſt exaltation or beſt capacities of power and intereſt, yet they are no proper ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of our truſt and dependance.</p>
            <p n="3">3ly. We ſhall inquire whether we may have no recourſe to, or expectation from, any humane aſſiſtance in time of need.</p>
            <p n="4">4ly. Conſider what improvement may be made to our advantage.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label>1ſt. Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral.</label> 1ſt. In our preſent ſtate and circumſtances we ſtand in need of help and relief. If we be conſidered in our natural capacities, we are not ſelf-ſufficient. It cannot be ſaid of us, as of the Oak and the Teyl-tree,<note place="margin">Iſai. 6.13.</note> that we have our Subſtance in our ſelves, nor that Seed or Sap within us, which can ſpring up with freſh ſupplies, and recruit the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cays of nature, giving it a green and flouriſhing dreſs, as often as its Leaves ſhed, or the top of her Carmel withers. Our Ciſterns like the Brook <hi>Cherith</hi> are often dry, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently exhauſted. A good Man in this ſenſe cannot be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied from himſelf, his hungry and thirſty appetite teaches him to ſpeak the Language of the Horſe-leech, give, give. What need the Raven to have been commiſſioned to carry the Prophet Bread and Fleſh in the Morning, and Bread and Fleſh in the Evening, if his wants had not returned upon him like an armed Man? Though our Lamps for the preſent may ſhine brightly, yet they'll ſoon go out, if not kept alive with frequent recruits, and new infuſions of Oyl. The natural heat of a Man is a fire that cannot laſt long, if there were not conſtant ſupplies of fuel to maintain it. The wiſe Man ſaith, <hi>where no wood is there the fire goes out.</hi> Prov.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106293:6"/>26.20. <hi>The eyes of all wait upon the Lord for their meat in due ſeaſon;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 104.27.</note> by which attendance on his Providence, our wants are not only imply'd and intimated, but clearly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved upon us.</p>
            <p>
               <label>N="2ly. Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick.</label> Nor are we barely to be conſidered in our natural, but alſo in our Politick capacities, in which we often meet with ſuch imbroilment in our affairs, and intanglement in the croud of thoſe occurrences which come croſs, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter upon us, that we many times know not which foot to ſet forward, or how to direct our ſteps. St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us in <hi>Acts</hi> 27.20. <hi>That neither Sun, Moon, nor Stars for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny days appeared to them, nor no ſmall tempeſt laid upon them, inſomuch that all hope of being ſaved was taken away.</hi> And thus it proved in our late conflict with unreaſonable Men, the Veſſel of our Church and State too was ſorely afflicted and toſſed with tempeſt.</p>
            <p>We were in ſuch diſtreſs, that all hope of being ſaved was taken away: If he, who was our Pilot and ſteered our Ship had not held the Winds in his fiſt, whom therefore thoſe Storms and Waves obey'd; he ſtilled the raging of the Sea, he quieted the madneſs of the People, who were ſo turbulent and impetuous, that which way ſoever we look'd they caſt a ſad and fatal aſpect upon us. We were in peril of falſe Brethren, in peril of our own Country-men, in peril of Strangers, perſecuted, afflicted, tormented on every ſide, we knew not which way to turn our ſelves ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the right hand, or to the left, ſo that in the midſt of life we were in death, which put us upon ſeeking ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, but not of Princes, or of the Son of Man, for in them there was no help. Which brings me to the ſecond thing I deſigned to ſpeak to, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2ly. That conſidering Men in their beſt capacities, or advantages of power and intereſt, yet they are not proper objects of our truſt and dependance. We may catch hold upon theſe twigs, but they cannot bear our weight, or
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106293:6"/>keep us from ſinking, when the Waters of <hi>Mara</hi> over-flow our Banks, or run over our Heads. All their power and intereſt are but faint and feeble things, ineffectual expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients to ſave either themſelves or others. 'Tis true, they may by great and ſwelling Titles be dignified and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed from others, but theſe are but <hi>magni nominis um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broe:</hi> And who can ſit under thoſe ſhadows and be ſafe? They are bubbles tunned with Air which with the Breath of God's Noſtrils are preſently ſtaved and ſtifled, and in a moment blaſted, ſo as never to appear: For when the Breath of God goeth forth theirs is ſtopp'd, and they return to the Earth from whence they were taken. But I ſhall give ſome particular reaſons to prove, that they are not ſufficient objects of our truſt. And here I ſhall ſhoot no other Arrows, or Arguments, than which we find in the quiver of the Text. The Crowns of Princes may adorn their Heads, but can never ſecure either theirs, or ours from falling. They may ſparkle with Diamonds, and be inrich'd with Jewels, but they are Pearls of no very great price upon this account, ſeeing Man in his beſt eſtate is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together vanity. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.5.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. They are not fit to be relied upon, becauſe they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not help nor relieve us.] And then what need we any other proof? We have heard the Lord's own words. <hi>[Truſt not in Princes, nor in the Son of Man in whom there is no help.]</hi> So that all ſurther arguments are ſuperſeded, if this be juſtified, which will not be difficult to do, whilſt it appears, that the Crowns of Princes are not placed ſo high as to be out of Gun-ſhot, or above the reach of thoſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, which are incident to the reſt of Mankind. There Perſons are not peculiars, or that can plead the prerogative of Exemption, from thoſe temptations and trials which afflict others. If ſo, their name would be a ſtrong tower, and thoſe, who are in diſtreſs might flee to it, and be ſafe; but this have proved a weak reſuge unto others, whilſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106293:7"/>they have not been able to ſecure themſelves from the ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings of the People.<note place="margin">Jan. 30.</note> As the ſad theme of this day is no weak evidence, for the anointed of the Lord was taken in their net, who ſaid we will not have this Man rule over us, but brought him, and ſlew him at the gates of his Palace. How low were the five Kings of the <hi>Amorites</hi> laid, when the Captains of <hi>Joſhua</hi> ſet their feet upon their<note n="*" place="margin">Joſh. 10.24.</note> necks? Nor could the Imperial Crown which <hi>Frederick</hi> wore defend him from the inſult of Pope <hi>Alexander,</hi> who was baſely tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled on by his holineſs, or haughtineſs rather, perverting holy writ to an unintended Senſe. <hi>Thou ſhalt tread upon the Lion and Adder, the young Lion and the Dragon thou ſhalt trample under thy feet, Pſal.</hi> 91.13. How then can they cover us with their feathers? or under their Wings can we truſt? How can they be a ſtrong tower to us from the faces of our Enemies, who themſelves are too often expoſed to their fury, and become a prey to their revenge? It might be well enough ſaid concerning <hi>Saul,</hi> How ſhall this Man ſave us, who could not ſecure himſelf upon the Throne, but had his Kingdom rent from him, like the skirt of his Garment? Shall we then lean againſt a bowing Wall, or tottering Fence, which are ſo little able to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port us, that they cannot be a ſufficient ſtay to their own ſhaking States, or declining Empires? Let us therefore ceaſe from Men, who though they be tunned full with po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular air, yet their breath is in their noſtrils, which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently goes forth, and they return to the Earth, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces the ſecond Argument.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly. <hi>Viz.</hi> That it is not wiſedom to confide in the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Men, becauſe they are mortal and muſt die.] Who would hang too much weight upon that ſilver Cord, which is ſo preſently looſed, or fill their Pitcher with any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious liquor, which is ſo unexpectedly broken at the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, leaving all our expectation and hope like water ſpilt upon the ground, never to be retrieved or gathered up
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106293:7"/>again? For Man dies, his breath goes forth, that is, the Soul departs, and his body returns to the Earth, being then reduced to its firſt original; for duſt it was,<note place="margin">Ecal. 12.7.</note> and to duſt it ſhall return, in which repoſitory it is only fit to be laid, and buried out of our ſight. Or perhaps the words may be thus read: The breath goes forth but never returns,<note place="margin">Egredie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur flatus ejus. Cald. Paraphr.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration ceaſeth, the motion of the ſpirits, and circulation of the blood is for ever ſtopt, upon which ſtagnation of the humours, the body preſently ſtinks and is corrupt, fit for nothing but its long home, and common receptacle, where it is reduced to its firſt Principle. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.7. <hi>Then ſhall the duſt return to the Earth as it was, and the ſpirit to God who gave it.</hi> Nor is it long to this period; we have not far to travel before we come to the grave, the knot which is tied upon the thread of Life, is eaſily and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly looſed: We dwell in Cottages that are of Clay, but we have no leaſe of them, or if we had, 'tis the Owner, not the Tenant which preſcribes the term of it, which is not ſpun out to any great length. For yet a little while and ye ſhall ſee us, and yet a little while and ye ſhall not ſee us, becauſe we are going to our long home. And no wonder, for whilſt we live we may be ſaid to die daily, we being no ſooner quit from the Womb, but we are haſting to the Tomb. Our Sun being like that in the Firmament, which from its firſt riſing is immediately po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting towards its declenſion and fall, only with this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that this never goes down till it hath run its race, and finiſh'd its courſe, for though it may be ſometimes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentally eclipſed, yet it recovers its light and luſtre again, keeping itſelf always above-board, till the ſhadows of the Evening be drawn over it. When ours many times ſets, before 'tis well up, or when it is in its higheſt exaltation, or vertical point of health and ſtrength, age or honour, ſinks into the place of darkneſs, and goes down into the Land of Forgetfullneſs. As the deceaſe of our late Gracious Queen is too ſad, and pertinent an inſtance.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:106293:8"/>
            <p>Which comes to paſs, firſt, from the nature of our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution and State, we are made of heavy Clay, which hath always a tendency and inclination downward, and would drop into the Earth from whence it came (that being the hole of the pit from whence we are digged) if the conſtant kindneſs and care of Heaven did not prevent the fall. The Beams of our own timber have thoſe worms in them, that though there ſhould be none to pull down, and dilapidate our Buildings, they would fall into decay of their own accord. But 2dly. There be many accidents which drive us faſter, and give us ſpeedier diſpatches out of this World, than what may be ordinarily expected from the common infirmities, and decays of nature. The thread of life, which might have laſted ſome time, is ſuddenly by a violent hand cut off, before it be ſpun to half the length, to which its ſtaple might in the courſe of nature have been drawn, and by a violent juſtle we are ſhuft into the Grave; where, and when all our thoughts periſh: Which brings me to the third Argument which juſtifies the Doctrine.</p>
            <p n="3">3ly. When we be once dead all our<note n="*" place="margin">Purpoſes Ainſw. <hi>Eccl. 9.10.</hi> No work, vice, nor knowledge, norwiſdom, <hi>&amp;c. repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te uno mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento concidunt conſilia. Jun. &amp; Trem.</hi> All their worldly contrivan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated and evacuated. <hi>Hammon.</hi>
               </note> thoughts, all our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects and forecaſts, all our counſels and contrivances give up the Ghoſt. Nor is there any counſel, device, or policy in the Grave, whither we are going. When Man dies, not only the form of his countenance is changed, but the faſhion of all his deſigns paſſes away. The neſt which is built, with ſo much art and contrivance, though pitch'd upon the higheſt branches, when the Tree is hewn up falls down, and is levelled with the duſt. Who then would put his truſt in Princes, or build his hope upon thoſe (tho tall and ſtately) Cedars which to day are the glory of the Grove, but to morrow become a prey to the Ax, their high and towring tops laid low and level with the ground? With death there is no reſpect of Perſons, he that feareth God, and he that feareth him not, he that is high, and he that is low; yet in this reſpect ſtand upon the ſame level,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106293:8"/>and are upon even ground. <hi>Job</hi> 34.19, 20. <hi>God accepteth not the Perſons of Princes, nor regardeth the rich more than the poor, for they are all the work of his hands; in a moment they ſhall die and the mighty ſhall be taken away without hand,</hi>] and then all their thoughts periſh, the day of life is the time for labour, when the night of death comes no Man can work? Now the grinders ceaſe, and thoſe that look out of the Windows be dark'ned, and the deſire ſhall fail, becauſe Man goeth to his long home, and the mourners go about the ſtreets. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.3, 4, 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ahitophel</hi> was a Man of great Wiſdom and Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, but when his Breath was ſtopp'd, his Mouth was ſhut too, all his thoughts periſhed, nor could there beany further opportunity to conſult that Oracle; he could give no more counſel to his Maſter, his Soul was departed, he was gone down into the pit, where he could think no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, nor aſſiſt <hi>Abſalom</hi> any further with his advice; he had done framing ſtratagems of War, or projects for Peace, he was returned to his Earth, where all his thoughts periſh'd, and ſo might his Maſter too for all him, in whom there was no help.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> But is there no help in Man, nor truſt to be had in Perſons of the higheſt degree? Shall we ſay of them as they ſaid of <hi>Saul,</hi> how ſhall this Man ſave us, will not this cauſe us to deſpiſe Magiſtrates, and to pour out contempt upon Princes?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
               </label> The Laws of the firſt table are no way repugnant to the commands of the ſecond, like parallel lines, or thoſe drawn from the ſame Centre, to whatever length they are produced do never croſs, nor cut each other. The ſame Apoſtle, which bids us fear God, does at the ſame time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>join us to honour the King, who is ſet on high, as a Candle upon an Hill, that we may have an eye upon him, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to him. It's true, the ſecond cauſe ought not to be reverenced as, nor ranked in the ſame order with the firſt,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106293:9"/>but only to be conſidered as it's moved by, and actuated from, the ſupreme agent. Our wheels would ſtand ſtill were they not driven on by the Elaſtick force and power of the Spring. The Diſciples had no reaſon to ſacrifice to their own net, or skill for the great draught of Fiſh they caught; for till it pleaſed God to bring the Shole together, they laboured but in vain, they did <hi>magno conatu nihil age<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. Luke</hi> 5.5. But next to the influencing power of Divine Providence, inſeriour Agents may have their juſt eſteem and regard. We know indeed, that the race is not to the ſwift, nor the Battel to the ſtrong, nor riches to Men of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. But the over-ruling Power and Providence of God turns the Scales, and determines all things as pleaſeth him. Though in the ordinary method of his Government, he makes his Magiſtrates, who are but Men, to be Spirits, and thoſe Miniſters a flame of Fire, inſtruments in his hand for the ſafety of Mankind, conſidered either in a natural, civil, or ſpiritual capacity. To whom we may flee for ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour in our diſtreſs, as they are Meſſengers ſent by God to do his Will, and to be his Miniſters to us for good. Always reſerving the glory due to himſelf, as the ſupreme Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and univerſal Monarch of Heaven and Earth. Thoſe whom St. <hi>Paul</hi> healed were highly ſenſible of the favour, and paid a juſt reſpect for ſo great a kindneſs. They hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red us with many honours. <hi>Acts</hi> 28.10. But the Apoſtles were very carefull that God's honour ſhould not be aſcribed to the Creatures, who are only ſubſtitutes to act by his Authority and Power derived to them, for the purpoſes of his glory. <hi>Acts</hi> 3.12. <hi>And when St.</hi> Peter <hi>ſaw it, he anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the People, ye Men of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>why marvel ye at this, or why look ye ſo earneſtly on us, as though by our own Power or Holineſs we had made this Man walk. v.</hi> 16. <hi>His name, through faith in his name, hath made this Man ſtrong, whom ye ſee and know; yea, the faith which is by him hath given him this perfect ſoundneſs in the preſence of you all.</hi>]</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:106293:9"/>
            <p>Thus the Miniſters of God are not to be honoured, nor truſted to, as the firſt cauſe, and original fountain from whence our relief flows; yet they are thoſe conduits and conveyances, through which our help, that ſtream of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhments, which makes glad the City of God. And though Princes, as they are the Sons of Men, be in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves but faint and feeble things, yet they are oftentimes made ſtrong by the Power of the moſt High; ſo that our help is not only laid upon them, but they are made by him mighty to ſave thoſe who put their truſt in them.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. If we conſider, that the Authority by which they act is veſted in them from above.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly. The wiſdom of their Counſels; In the multitude of which there is ſafety.</p>
            <p n="3">3ly. The power of the Sword, which they do not bear in vain.</p>
            <p n="4">4ly. The intereſt of their Confederation and Alliances, by which they are better able to relieve the oppreſſed, and to help thoſe to right who ſuffer wrong.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. The Authority by which they act is veſted in them from above: They have their Credentials from Heaven, and their Commiſſions are ſealed there, from which topick St. <hi>Paul</hi> argues, and proves our ſubmiſſion to their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. Rom. 13.1. <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject to the higher powers, for there is no power but of God, the powers that be, are ordained of God; whoſoever therefore reſiſts the power, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God.</hi> Seeing then this Cedar is a Tree of the Lord's planting, why may we not ſit under the ſhadow of it with delight? And if any ſhall ſay, how ſhall this Man ſave us? or any Prince who is the Son of Man help us? we may reply, that he is God's Vicegerent and Deputy, deſigned not only to be a terrour to evil doers, but a praiſe and encouragement to them that do well. The Lord hath cauſed theſe gourds to ſpring up to ſhroud and ſhelter them. And then, why may we not with <hi>Jonah</hi> be
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106293:10"/>exceeding glad, and ſo far truſt in them, as God hath made them uſefull to ſecure and defend us from the heat and burthen of the day?</p>
            <p>Princes and Magiſtrates as they are Men, be made of the ſame metal with the reſt of Mankind, ſubject to the ſame infirmities with others of a lower rank and more debaſed Station; but whilſt they bear the Superſcription and Image of the Divine Authority ſtamp'd upon them, they are not only of more value by virtue of that Impreſſion, but may challenge the greater awe and veneration from us. Which may alſo excuſe us from the imputation of vain conſidence, whilſt we ſhroud our ſelves under the lee of their Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Government.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly. From the Wiſdom of their Counſels.] This is another ſinew and ligament of Civil Government. 2 Kings 18.20. <hi>Thou ſay'ſt I have counſel and ſtrength for the War.</hi>] That ſometimes out-does force, is more than its match, and carries it headlong, avoiding its ſtrongeſt attempts, baffling and defeating the moſt powerful eſſays it can make to our deſtruction. This you may ſee verified in <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.14. <hi>There was a little City and few Men within it, and there came a great King againſt it and beſieged it, and built great Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warks againſt it, and there was found in it a poor wiſe Man, who by his Wiſdom delivered the City, then ſaid I Wiſdom is better than ſtrength.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
               </label> But you will ſay Princes are not always Wiſe, nor great Men always Good: The Lord ſometimes gives a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Children to be their Princes,<note place="margin">They err in Viſion, they ſtumble in Judgment. <hi>Iſai. 28.7.</hi>
               </note> and Babes to rule over them, and carries their Counſel headlong. <hi>Job</hi> 5.13. This was no ſmall Plague upon <hi>Egypt:</hi> When the Princes of <hi>Zoan</hi> were Fools, and the Counſel of the Wiſe Counſellors of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> was become brutiſh. From hence it was that <hi>Egypt</hi> erred in every Work thereof, as a drunken Man ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gereth in his Vomit. And ſo may we reel too and fro, if we put our truſt in them, or in the Wiſdom of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:106293:10"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
               </label> This is but an accidental puniſhment of a wicked People, whom the Lord deſigns to deſtroy; and ſo he makes their infatuation not only a Preſage and Preface, but cauſe of their ruine. <hi>Quos perdere vult dementat prius.</hi> Thus when the Lord deſigned to puniſh <hi>Ahab,</hi> and that he might ſall a prey at <hi>Ramoth Gilead;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King 12.15.</note> he put a lying Spirit into the mouths of his Prophets and Counſellors. So did the Lord hide counſel from <hi>Rehoboam;</hi> nor did he hearken to the counſel of the Old Men, for the cauſe was from the Lord, that he might rend the Kingdom out of the hand of <hi>Solomon,</hi> as he ſpake by <hi>Ahijah</hi> the <hi>Shilonite</hi> to <hi>Jeroboam.</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11.31. So far was the heart of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> hard'ned, that he would not believe nor be adviſed by <hi>Moſes,</hi> God having purpoſed his ruine in the <hi>Red Sea;</hi> for that deſpite perhaps, which he had ſhown to his peculiar People, that were Pilgrims with him in a ſtrange Land.</p>
            <p>But the ordinary end of God's ſetting Rulers over his People is, that they may be his Miniſters to them for good, that they may be a ſhelter to them from the ſtorm, and keep them quiet from the fear of evil. To this end he gives them wiſe and underſtanding Hearts, that they may be able to go in and out before the People, and that they may find paſture to refreſh them. Hence it is,<note place="margin">Pſ. 105.22.</note> that the Lord counſels our Counſellors and teacheth our Senators Wiſdom; putting this eye into their Heads, by which they ſee the things which concern the Peace and Welfare of their Subjects, guiding their hands in managing the Helm, and ſleering the Veſſel or Ship of the Common-wealth, through a troubleſome Sea into a ſafe and ſecure Harbour. Now though we know, that he who gathers the Winds in his Fiſt, and binds the Waters in a Garment: He whom the Seas obey, is the ſupreme Pilot;<note place="margin">Prov. 30.4.</note> yet it cannot but calm the Minds of the Paſſengers in the midſt of thoſe ſtorms they meet with, that he hath deputed one, whom he ordinarily endues with a Spirit of Government; on
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106293:11"/>whom next to himſelf they truſt and rely upon for help, though he be but the Son of Man.</p>
            <p n="3">3ly. The Power of the Sword,] which he bears not in vain, for he is by that a terrour to evil doers, but a praiſe and defence to thoſe that do well. By this as it were with a trident he ſtills the raging of the Sea, I mean quiets the madneſs of the People. Whether we take this for the civil or military Sword, they have either of them power and edge enough, to out in pieces, and hamſtring a mutinous and rebellious People; to charm, or awe the unpeaceable and otherwiſe ungovernable tempers of turbulent and unru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Men, that we may lead a peaceable and quiet life in godlineſs and honeſty. They have a power to turn and brandiſh theſe every way, as the Angel his flaming Sword over the Tree of Life; that none of our Enemies at home, or Foes abroad may prevail againſt us, or approach to hurt us. And may we not brood and ſhelter our ſelves under the Wings of that Government, which God hath impowered to ſhelter us from the talons of thoſe Hawks, which elſe would prey upon us? May we not with due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the Divine Providence, truſt to the Wiſdom and Conduct of him whom God hath ſet over us; and whom he hath taught to manage both thoſe Weapons, I mean his civil and military Power, whom God hath enabled to defend the innocent from thoſe who ſmite with the Fiſt of wickedneſs? We have found one that ſeeks judgment, and relieves the oppreſſed, who judgeth the Fatherleſs, and pleads for the Widow. One who hath broach'd that Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, whoſe Waters make glad the City of God: I mean judgment which runs down as water, and righteouſneſs as a mighty ſtream. Time was, <hi>that inſtead of well ſet hair we had baldneſs, inſtead of a girdle a rent, inſtead of a ſweet ſavour a ſtink;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 3.24.</note> and no wonder for judgment ſprang up like hemlock in the furrows of the Field. The Prophet tells us of Princes that were rebellious, and Companions of Thieves,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106293:11"/>who judged not the Fatherleſs, neither did the cauſe of the Widow come up before them.<note place="margin">Iſai. 1.23.</note> Oh how was our faithfull City become an Harlot, righteouſneſs lodged in it, but then Murtherers?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai. 5.7.</hi> We looked for judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but behold op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion for rightcouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a cry.</note> When the civil Sword of Juſtice was no better than a murthering knife, which ſhed the blood of many an innocent and eminent Perſon, and Patriot of his Country. When the greateſt cruelty and oppreſſion put on the garb of juſtice, and form of Law: Whilſt it made havock in the midſt of us, ripping up the Bowels of thoſe Worthies, and rifling their Families for no other crime, than the love they bore to our Church and State, our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Properties; for ſtanding in the gap and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our bank againſt the ſwelling tide of that Religion, which hath neither God for its Author, nor his word for its rule. Oh the oppreſſion that was then in our Gates! the Complaints that were then in our Streets, which as they rent our hearts, and deafned our ears, ſo they entred into the Ears of the Almighty, who heard our cry and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered us when we were in our diſtreſs. When our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was deſerted the civil and military Swords were, like the Shield of <hi>Saul</hi> upon Mount <hi>Gilboa,</hi> vilely caſt away; God was pleaſed to put them into a more ſteady hand, and ſtretched-out arm, which have wounded our Enemies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Fifth Rib, that the very Bowels of that deſign for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med againſt us are guſh'd out, as having received its fatal ſtroke, and deadly wound, never to live or revive more; if we do not again weave the Spider's Web, or hatch the Cockatrice Eggs, which neither now nor formerly could have been ſprung ſo ſucceſsfully, had not an over-glowing zeal (for we ſcarce knew what, brooded and enforced them.</p>
            <p>Too many of which have ſuck'd in that Venome, which we find hard to expel. No antidote that we can meet with in the diſpenſatories, either of Scripture or Reaſon, have proved ſufficiently effectual to root out the Poiſon of thoſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106293:12"/>Doctrines, which in the time of their defection they drank out of the Cup of Abominations; I mean of that great Whore, which cauſed many in our faithful City to become Harlots, who were once the Virgin Daughters of our <hi>Sion;</hi> but have more reaſon than <hi>Jephthah</hi>'s in another ſenſe, to go upon the Mountains and bewail their Virginity, who ſuffered themſelves to be deſiled and deflowered, enticed and ſeduced by the Pimps and Panders of their Religion: Parting with their precious Faith for thoſe Beads and Brace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets they carry in their hands, ſelling their Religion, which was far more valuable than Silver, yea, more to be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med than fine Gold, for thoſe ſacred toys, and conſecrated baubles, which have proved a dearer purchaſe than thoſe Apes and Peacocks, which the Merchants of <hi>Hiram</hi> tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for.</p>
            <p>But when will theſe Runagades return and remember from whence they are fallen? The worſt we wiſh them is, that they would be zealous and repent. The Lord hath given you a ſpace of repentance, and if you repent not, he will caſt you,<note place="margin">Rev. 2.5.</note> and thoſe you have committed Fornication with, into a Bed of great tribulation. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.21, 22. The Lord would purge you, but if you will not be purged, how juſtly may he ſay you ſhall not be purged, until I cauſe my fury to reſt upon you? But I have followed theſe ſtraying Brethren too far out of the way; and therefore 'tis time to return, and bleſs that Divine Goodneſs, which hath placed a Prince upon the Throne, and girded him with a Sword, which hath defended us from the Enemy and Avenger, Oppreſſion at home, and Violence from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad; he hath kept that Wolf from our doors, which is fat with the Blood of the Slain, his murthered Subjects and Neighbours; as if the words of the Prophet were fulfilled in our days. <hi>Behold a King ſhall Reign in righteouſneſs, and a Prince ſhall rule in judgment: And a Man ſhall be as an hiding place from the Wind, and a covert from the Tempeſt,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106293:12"/>as rivers of water in a dry place, as the ſhadow of a great rock in a weary land.</hi> Iſa. 32.1, 2.</p>
            <p n="4">4ly. The Intereſt of their Confederations and Alliances; though a ſingle Arrow may be ſoon ſnapt, yet a bundle of them is of that united force, as not to be readily broken. If Princes take Counſel together they ſtand the ſtronger, if they aſſociate themſelves they cannot be caſily broken in pieces: Like the ſides of a roof, they lean againſt, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port one another. By means of a ſtrict Alliance and Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation, our neighbouring Provinces quitted themſelves from an heavy Yoke, and horrid Inquiſition. And though they were at no ſmall expence of Blood and Treaſure, in aſſerting their Liberties; yet by God's bleſſing, and their ſteady union, they became their own Men in deſpite of that project, which was framed to make them<note n="*" place="margin">See the Hiſtory of the Wars of <hi>Flanders</hi> by Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Benti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voglio.</hi> Book firſt.</note> Slaves to <hi>Spain,</hi> and Vaſſals to <hi>Rome.</hi> The Profeſſors of whoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion being like thoſe who are infected with the Plague; they are not contented to be miſerable alone, but have (as they ſay it is the nature of that Diſeaſe) a paſſionate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to convey it unto others. Being a ſpeckled and ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraked Herd; they cannot endure thoſe who have not the like ſpots and blemiſhes with themſelves. And that our ſtate and circumſtances had been this day incomparably ſad, there's none among us (who was not confederate with the Enemies of our Church and State) ſo ſlow of heart to believe, but will confeſs, had not our Friends and Allies come over and helped us; who being tempted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, knew the better how to relieve and ſuccour thoſe that were tempted; yea, at this very day, there is an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing ſcourge, which bears hard againſt us, threatning that fatal deluge which will make our Land bright with miſery, or our Fields red with Blood; but thanks be to God more Hands than our own are at Work, to prevent the Breach, and maintain our Bank againſt them. And why may we not ſo far truſt in him, whom God hath ſet
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106293:13"/>over us, as joined in Alliance with thoſe Potent Princes and States, that have counſel and ſtrength for the War, as is conſiſtent with a due regard to the Divine Providence? And though in the Sons of Men there be no help, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently no confidence to be had in them, ſeparately and in themſelves conſidered; yet as united together, and eſpecially as influenced with Power from above, they may become mighty to ſave; a ſtaff of Bands which will not run into our hands and pierce us, though we lean upon it. But leſt we ſhould improve this too far, as if we argued againſt the Text, let us take the Prophet's advice, and <hi>ceaſe from Man whoſe breath is in his noſtrils, for wherein is he to be accounted of?</hi> Iſai. 2.22. The Pſalmiſt places him in the beſt light, and conſiders him in the higheſt exaltation, and moſt advantageous circumſtances; and yet at laſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, <hi>that it's better to truſt in the Lord than to put confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in man; yea, it's better to truſt in the Lord than to put confidence in Princes.</hi> Pſal. 118.9. He was a King himſelf, who in the Siege of <hi>Samaria</hi> ſaid to the Woman, when ſhe cryed in her extremity, <hi>If the Lord does not help thee, whence ſhould I?</hi> 2 Kings 6.27. If then we ſhall be ſuch fooliſh Builders as to lay our Foundation on the Sand, we ſhall need no Spirit of Prophecy to foretell the fate of our Structure. We may drink of the Brook in the way, and refreſh our ſelves with thoſe running ſtreams. But if we do not lift up the head to Heaven, and own that to be the Fountain in which are all our freſh Springs, we forget our Maker, hewing to our ſelves Ciſterns, which though they be not broken, yet are of that limited meaſure, and ſtinted capacity, that they are ſoon exhauſted and drawn dry, not affording one drop of reſreſhment to a thirſty and panting Soul.</p>
            <p n="4">4ly. What improvement may we make from hence?</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:106293:13"/>
            <p n="1">1ſt. The firſt thing I ſhall give an hint of is; that if we may not ſeek for ſhelter under the protection and lee of Soveraign Power, what help can we expect from the Sons of Men, placed in a lower rank and inferiour order? If there be no ſecurity or bleſſing to be had under the warm Sun; what influence can we hope for, from the leſſer Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets? If a ſhield of braſs can't defend us, but we are pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced through with divers cares and ſorrows, how can a cobweb ſhroud us, or quench thoſe fiery darts which are ſhot at us? This have been ſufficiently experimented by thoſe, who notwithſtanding the intereſt of their Friends and Families, their honourable Alliances, with Perſons of great Wealth and noble Extraction, yet could never be ſecured from the moſt fatal ſtroke, but have fallen as a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to the rage and malice of their implacable and bloody Enemies. I could name many of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triots, which ſtood in the gap till they were ſwept away with that over-flowing tide, which bore ſo hard upon them.</p>
            <p>But what need we put a difference betwixt Perſons of the higheſt, and thoſe of a more inferiour order, <hi>when Men of low degree are vanity, and Men of high degree are a lie.</hi> Pſ. 62.9.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly. And therefore ſeeing that they are too weak to ſupport us, it were well they would not lean too hard up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on themſelves; that they would not ſuppoſe their neſt to be built upon a Rock, too ſtrong to be ſorced, too high to be climbed. Alas! as to their natural capacities they are made of the ſame maſs with the reſt of Mankind; it hath pleaſed the Potter to make the Veſſel of honour and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the ſame Clay; ſo that the Princes Pitcher is as ſoon broken at the Fountain as the Peaſants, who upon this account are upon even terms; the Cedars and the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comores grow upon the ſame level, being equally obno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xious to the dint of the Ax, and violence of the Winds. Iſai.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106293:14"/>10.33. <hi>The Lord of Hoſts will lop the bough with ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and the high ones of ſtature ſhall be hewn down.</hi> This day was this Scripture fulfilled among us,<note place="margin">Jan. 30.</note> when it pleaſed God to ſuffer the talleſt Cedar in our Foreſt to become a Prey to the Ax, and to be hewed up at the very roots. He that was ſet over us by God, to be our Ruler, and Supreme Prince and Governour, was given up to the ſtrivings of the People, and fell as a Sacrifice to their fury at the Gates of his Palace, where he laid beſmeared in his Blood, as though he had not been anointed with Oyl. Oh! tell it not in <hi>Gath,</hi> publiſh it not in the Streets of <hi>Askelon,</hi> leſt the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Philiſtines</hi> triumph, leſt thoſe uncircumciſed in hearts and ears ſhould rejoice, who decry ſometimes the fact as unpardonable, which would have been eſteemed by them a thing meritorious (as taking off ſo great an Enemy to their Cauſe) had it been perpetrated by the hand of a <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit,</hi> or <hi>Jacobine Frier.</hi> But this is a ſore which proceſs of time hath skinned over, and I am very unwilling to rub it till it bleeds afreſh. 'Tis pity to blow thoſe Embers which are almoſt dead and buried in their own Aſhes into a new Flame, and enkindle freſh heart-burnings among us. What we have now to do is, to endeavour to attone (if it may be) our former defects of duty to thoſe who were ſet over us, by doubling our acts of Loyalty and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to that Prince who now Reigns among us; who hath endeared himſelf to us by all that could oblige a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, and (I wiſh there were not too much reaſon to ſay) an ungrateful People. Who being as Fire-brands pluck'd out of the fire ſo lately extinguiſhed, are bringing new fewel, and by ſparks of their own, endeavouring to kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle it: Striving to bring back, and cauſe a reverſe of all thoſe miſeries, which this bleſſed inſtrument in the hand of Divine Providence, ſo effectually ſaved and reſcued us out of; as if the extirpation of our Faith and Religion were a proper object of our zeal, and fit imployment for
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106293:14"/>our new Ambition. And as if Oppreſſion and Slavery (the Burthens we ſo lately groaned under) were now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the matter of our choice, and valued as Pearls of the greateſt price. Which looks as if we could be eaſie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der nothing more than thoſe calamities and miſeries, which were but as yeſterday, the ſad and diſmal Theme of our Complaints. We had no ſooner taſted of liberty, and but juſt ſeen how good it was, but our teeth are ſet on edge for thoſe ſour Grapes which made us cry out, our Bowels, our Bowels, we are pained at the very heart: Accounting our <hi>Moſes</hi> whom God ſent to deliver us, our great Task-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and only Oppreſſour. Wiſhing now we are got in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Canaan,</hi> a Land flowing with Milk and Honey; I mean our Liberties and Religion, that we might return into <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> and that we might again labour in thoſe brick-kilns and iron furnaces as in the fire. Theſe are ſo far from truſting in their Princes, that they are daily pouring out their Complaints, and Contempts upon them.</p>
            <p>But as Moral virtue hath an extremity on both hands, <hi>viz.</hi> a Gulph of defect on one ſide, and a Rock of exceſs on the other; ſo with ſuch like extremities have ſome among us been chargable in the caſe before us. For whilſt ſome have ſaid, how ſhall this Man ſave us, and brought him no preſents? Others have been apt to ſay, behold the God which delivered us out of the hands of our Enemies, who hath brought us out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> into <hi>Canaan;</hi> who hath bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off our Yoke, and tranſlated us into glorious light and liberty. It will then be the office, and art of Chriſtian Prudence to ſteer us ſo evenly, that whilſt we give to <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s; we may not rob God of his Glory, nor give it to another.</p>
            <p>We may reſt upon our ſtaff in our paſſage through the Wilderneſs, but we ought eſpecially to lean upon our Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved. Our deliverance have been very ſweet to our taſte, and we muſt be very ungratefull not to kiſs the hand that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106293:15"/>brought it to us: But we muſt not forget the Rock from whence it was hewn. We may value the ſtream, but we muſt eſpecially adore the Fountain, from whence it did originally flow. And have not our leaning ſo hard, and lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo great a ſtreſs upon our ſtaff cauſed it to buckle un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us, as we have obſerved already. Becauſe our Bow was doubly ſtrung, we ſaid that ſhall ſave us. Which perhaps is one ſin for which the Lord hath been diſpleaſed with us, and hath cauſed him to ſhoot that Arrow from Heaven, which hath ſlain one of our Princes; and hath juſtified the truth of that Maxime, that though they be ſtiled Gods, yet they ſhall die like Men. For her Breath is gone forth, ſhe is returned to the duſt. From which we ſee crowned Heads are no way exempt, nor privileged. A Providence which ſeems little leſs ſurprizing, than the command God gave to <hi>Abraham</hi> of ſacrificing his only Son, of whom it was ſaid in <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſhall thy Seed be called. We could not but think that the Honour of God, and Welfare of our Church, were juſtly provided for, when he had bleſt it with ſuch a nurſing Mother; we could not but hope, that Religion and Piety, which had ſo long been in a languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and valetudinary condition muſt needs have revived, and aſſumed new life and vigour, not only by the influence of her power, but warmth of her example, of whom with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out flattery it might have been ſaid, in reſpect to her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout and conſtant exerciſe of Religion, look on her and do likewiſe. For let a Prince weave never ſuch good Laws, a debauch'd and bad life unravels all the contexture. <hi>Regis ad exemplum totus componitur orbis.</hi> Men being more apt to faſhion themſelves by the Scheme of his actions, than the form of his Government. But when we had ſo great hopes, that Godhead effectually ſecured the true Religion, and ſettled the Kingdom of his dear Son, by promoting ſuch a Perſon to the Throne, whom he had ſo eminently fitted for ſuch great ends, and noble purpoſes. Our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106293:15"/>ſeemed like a Veſſel under a full Sail, fill'd with a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous and fair Gale, ſteering a ſteady courſe towards a deſired Port, we ſeemed ſecure of an happy arrival, as though we had attained, and our deliverance was already perfect, all fears of a Shipwrack were taken away. When, as it were in a moment, our Pilot drops, our Veſſel ſinks down to rights, and all the Cargo of our Hopes, and Thoughts on board there, periſhed. Good God! How un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable are thy ways, and how are thy paths paſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out? Thy ways are not as our ways, nor thy thoughts as our thoughts. It was thy doing, and therefore we ſhall be dumb, and not open our mouths to charge thee fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; that it may be ſaid of us, as it was of <hi>Job,</hi> in all this we did not ſin with our lips, <hi>for why ſhould we receive good, and not evil at the hand of the Lord?</hi> To what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is it to go to her grave to weep there, who though dead, yet methinks we hear yet ſpeaking; Weep not for me, but for your ſelves, and for your ſins, for which God is diſpleaſed? Theſe, theſe were the Traitors that ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned her Reign, and that would not let this excellent Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs to rule any longer over us. That have provoked God to take her from us. But though her Earthly Crown be fallen from her Head; yet this is our comfort, that we have good reaſon to believe, ſhe changed it for that which fadeth not away, reſerved in the Heavens for her. But what now remains is to do juſtice to our ſelves, I mean to bring thoſe ſins, thoſe Enemies which have done us this miſchief, and ſmite them and ſlay them, which have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived us of ſuch a Queen, as ſcarce ever adorned the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Throne; for though others may have done vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly; yet, ſhe hath excelled them all. <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.29.</p>
            <p>But yet we have <hi>poſt naufragium tabulam.</hi> The Lord hath left us a Prince upon the Throne, a Son of Man in whom we hope there may be ſome help; the Lord hath not left us comfortleſs without a Ruler, without a Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106293:16"/>one whom he once made able to ſave us. He hath delivered us, he doth deliver us, and we truſt God will by him ſtill deliver us; I mean our King, who yet lives, and long may he live to rule over us. To whom we ought to be ſubject for the Lord's ſake; yet not to place him in the Lord's ſtead. 'Tis true, the anointed of the Lord is the breath of our noſtrils, but his breath is in his too, which ſoon goes forth, and then he muſt return to his Earth, of which the inſtance I have given you of his Royal Conſort is a ſad, but convincing proof, who by a ſudden ſtroke is fallen in our high places, as though ſhe had not been anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Oyl. When ſhe was in a green and flouriſhing condition, it pleaſed the Lord to pluck up this Plant of Righteouſneſs by the Roots, under whoſe ſhadow we ſate with great delight. But we hope only to tranſplant her into a better place, into that Paradiſe where ſhe may be a Tree of Life for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>But I cannot diſmiſs you till I have added ſomething by way of reproof, of ſome ſpightfull and unreaſonable Men, who would ſorce a ſenſe from the words very far from the meaning of them? for though we ought not to repoſe our confidence, or put our truſt in Princes for relief, ſo neither ought we to offer deſpite to them, or pour out any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon them. The counſel which <hi>Solomon</hi> gave, was not to <hi>curſe the King in our thought, nor the Rich in our bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber, for the Bird of the air ſhall carry the voice, and that which hath wings ſhall reveal the matter.</hi> Eccl. 10.20. Yet, there's ſome who are troubled with the over-flowing of the Gall; who have vented their reſentments and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in many bitter Complaints. They ſay 'tis true, there's little reaſon to truſt in Princes, or in the Son of Man in whom there is no help; great (ſay they) was the freedom we ſanſied, the eaſe and liberty we flattered our ſelves with, from the late change and revolution of State; but we ſee, we did but change our Yoke, and put on new Fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106293:16"/>and for which we pay very dear too. Aſſeſsments return ſo often, and heavy upon us, that we are preſſed down under the inſufferable weight and burthen of them, till we ſcarce know how to provide for our Families, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Bread to eat, or Raiment to put on, and how then can we be content? 'Tis true, we enjoy the exerciſe of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but the ſour ſauce and bitter herbs which attend our Paſſover, make us even to abhor the Sacrifice it ſelf for their ſake. Would to God we were in <hi>Egypt,</hi> rather than thus to die in the Wilderneſs; for our promiſed Land proves no better. We were told of Milk and Honey; but inſtead thereof, we are filled with bitterneſs, and made drunk with Wormwood. The little Finger of the preſent Government, proving heavier than the Loins of our late Reign; and yet this is he, who was promiſed to deliver our <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of all its troubles. And theſe be ſome of thoſe grievances, which are wrung, or rather poured out of their Cup, which is ſo full of the tears of their Complaints.</p>
            <p>When the hand of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> was upon us, and when we were ſwelkt in the iron Furnaces; Oh then! how ſtrong were our cries, by which we ſollicited Heaven to ſend a <hi>Moſes</hi> to deliver us? When we laboured as in the fire, how fervent were our Prayers for a <hi>Lazarus</hi> to cool our inflamed tongues? which we gnawed for anguiſh, when we durſt not uſe them in venting thoſe Paſſions, which like fire burnt within. But when it pleaſed God to deliver us, and ſet us at liberty from thoſe hard Task-maſters; Oh! then how eaſie was the Yoke, and light was that Burthen, which like <hi>Iſſachar</hi> we ſunk and buckled under? Now we look back to <hi>Sodom,</hi> and wiſh our ſelves in thoſe Flames, out of which we were ſo lately pluck'd as Firebrands. 'Tis true our Taxes run high, but no higher than the emergency of our Affairs, and neceſſity of our State require. And ſhall we grutch to part with ſome of our Earth to maintain our Banks, which are a Barrier againſt that ſwelling Tide which
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106293:17"/>bears ſo hard upon us? Or had we rather that over-flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſcourge ſhould break into, and paſs through our Land, and turn it into a Field of Blood? Shall we let our Veſſel ſink rather than caſt ſome part of our lading over-board? When <hi>Mahomet</hi> was coming up againſt <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> their Emperour ſent to the Citizens to aid him with Money, that he might defend them and their City from ſo barbarous and cruel an Enemy. But they made ſome petty excuſes as we now-a-days, <hi>viz.</hi> Alas! I cannot do it, I have a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily to provide for: Though we may be threatned, yet what we fear may never come upon us. Our danger is remote, and <hi>Hannibal</hi> is not yet at our Gates; nor hath the wicked approached ſo nigh as to hurt us. And thus they dallied with their own fate, till their impending ruin fell upon them like a milſtone, and ground them to pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: Who became a rich and eaſie prey to the rage and ravage of a Blood-thirſty and implacable Enemy; who not only rifled the treaſures they were ſo ſtanch of, but ſatiated himſelf with their Blood: Commanding at every Meal ſo many of the Nobility to be Beheaded, as might glut his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, whilſt he was pampering of his Body: Fulfilling the words of our Saviour with ſome alteration; He that will ſave his Life and Eſtate, ſhall loſe it, but he that will looſe his Life and Eſtate for his King and Country's ſake, the ſame ſhall ſave it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But let not us murmur as ſome of theſe alſo murmured,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 14.37.</note> 
               <hi>and were deſtroyed of the deſtroyer.</hi> 1 Cor. 10.10.</p>
            <p>Time was when an extravagant loyalty was the whole duty of Man; when Non-reſiſtance and Paſſive-obedience, were the fundamental Articles of their Faith, which in the leaſt to diſpute or doubt of, went for Hereſie or Treaſon.</p>
            <p>But now there's no Fetters ſtrong enough to cramp the Prerogative of the Prince, or curb his power, nor greater ſervice to be done to the Common-wealth, than to put a bridle into the mouth, and hook into the noſtrils of Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106293:17"/>Authority: Accounting thoſe who are inveſted with it, like the Horſe or Mule which hath no underſtanding. Theſe are they, who not long ſince would conſtrue the looks, and ſtrein Men's words of no bad ſenſe, to accuſe them of diſloyalty, and cauſe them to ſuffer by <hi>innueudo's.</hi> But now to diſobey Magiſtrates, to diſown, and deny Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to their Prince, is a vertue they bear themſelves upon.</p>
            <p>Some Men have been ſo wiſe and modeſt, that if they had any Opinion or Faith contrary to their duty, they would keep it to themſelves, that they might not affront the Powers that were in being, nor expoſe themſelves to their juſt cenſures. But theſe are ſpitting their Poiſon where-ever they come, huſſing and hiſſing at every one that is not of ſo poiſonous a brood as themſelves. And that they may be known to be ſo, wear ſome diſtinguiſhing Character, and by mark, that their folly may be known to all Men. Which they durſt not do, if they did not put their truſt in a Prince, whom we hope God is about to humble, and depend upon the Son of Man, that ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be able to help them. <hi>But whilſt ſome truſt in Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots, and ſome in Horſes, we will remember the name of the Lord our God. For happy is the Man who hath the God of Jacob for his refuge; yea, bleſſed are the People,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 20.7</note> 
               <hi>who have the Lord for their God.</hi> Which is a much ſafer retreat than we can otherwiſe make, <hi>by putting our truſt in Princes, or in the Son of Man, in whom there is no help.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
